Every programmer has run into at least one sorting algorithm at one point in their career.
Today, I'm going to easily explain 10 of the most popular sorting algorithms,  as well as the pros and cons of each.
Let's go.
BubbleSaur is one of the most popular sorting algorithms,  probably because it's the easiest.
BubbleSaur has an index that goes to the entire list.
If the number is on is larger than the next item, it switches them and then moves forward.
It then repeats this until every single item in the list has properly been solved.
And, understandably, BubbleSaur has terrible performance,  and is only ever used to teach how sorting algorithms work.
So algorithms are usually determined by time and space complexity.
No Weinstein, not that time and space.
Meaning, what's the best and worst case scenario of how fast it can go as well as the  amount of space it consumes?
So, the worst case for BubbleSaur is big O of N squared,  while the best case is big O of N.
Here's what that means in English.
N is universally understood as the number of items in the list you want to sort.
List.
Array.
Sorry, my Python is showing.
In our best case scenario, the array is already sorted,  so we need only one loop through them all to determine that.
But on the worst case scenario,  we would have to exponentially do an operation through this array in order for it to be sorted.
Meaning that if there were five items needing to be sorted,  we would have to do over 25 operations in order for it to be sorted.
So, do yourself a favor and just skip this one.
SelectionSaur is known as an in-place comparison sorting algorithm,  and it's actually fairly easy.
This algorithm divides the unsorted array into a sorted sublist,  which starts empty and the remaining items to sort, which is all of it for now.
The algorithm then goes one by one over the unsorted array looking for the smallest number.
Once the array has been completely looked over this iteration,  it then puts the smallest number at the end of the sublist.
This happens until all elements are gone and the array is fully sorted.
So, SelectionSaur has a worst case of Big O and Squared,  as well as the best case scenario of Big O and Squared.  Consistency.
Meaning just like BubbleSaur, SelectionSaur is not ideal at all.
And by the looks of it, arguably worse, right?
Well, SelectionSaur always seems to outperform BubbleSaur in most scenarios,  but there's better choices, so let's move forward.
So, InSertianSaur is very similar to SelectionSaur.
This sorting algorithm does one at a time by constantly comparing.
Here's how it works.
InSertianSaur, like SelectionSaur, it creates two arrays,  one sorted and one unsorted.
It goes through each element one by one in the unsorted array.
With the element that is on, it determines where in the sorted list,  the element belongs to by iterating over each element  to see if the number is between them.
Now, the worst case scenario is Big O and Squared,  while the best case is Big O and.
The thing with InSertianSaur is that it's been implemented  in C++ with only three lines of code.
And what's funny is that this is the sorting algorithm that you use  when you're holding up a bunch of cards and you need to sort them.
So, for very small lists, this might be a great option,  but when you're looking big, no.
MerSaur is a really popular and a really effective comparison-based sorting algorithm.
MerSaur fits in a category you'll see a lot in this video  under the divide and conquer algorithms.
First, take the unsorted array and divide it into the smallest unit,  which is usually just one element.
Then, you compare each element with the array next to it  and sort and merge the list.
Continue until you have one array that is completely sorted.
MerSaur has a worst case performance of Big O and Log N.
Here's what that means.
And, of course, represents the amount of numbers in our list.
Log N represents the amount of times N is divided.
So, if our unsorted array is 16, then Log N would be four.
Since we can divide 16 down to one and four iterations,  and best case is Omega and Log N.  Meaning, it doesn't get faster than this.
Essentially, whether your list is a bit sorted already or completely random,  MerSaur takes about the same amount of time to do his job,  making it reliably efficient.
But, where these divide and conquer algorithms really excel  is the ability to do things in parallel.
Since things are being split into many, many, many sublists,  dividing, sorting, and then merging can exponentially make things faster.
It's actually a really awesome algorithm.
QuickSaur is also one of the most popular algorithms that also uses  the divide and conquer sorting strategy.
Programming languages like JavaScript, Ruby, and PHP use QuickSaur  in their standard library features.
Is that a flex or...
So, QuickSaur works similar to MerSaur,  but requires something called a pivot.
In the unsorted array, pick a number to be your pivot.
This could be the first number, the last number, or the middle number.
The number that is chosen as the pivot is then used to compare  all values into one of each list,  less than or equal to the pivot, or more than the pivot.
A pivot point is then chosen within the newly created list  and do another comparison if it's greater or smaller.
Once it does this recursively to all sub arrays,  it is that considered sorted.
So, the worst case is big O and square,  while the best case is big O and log N.
But, as you can probably guess,  getting that pivot is an extremely important factor  in the performance of this algorithm.
So, some do the first, middle, or last element.
Others just do it randomly,  and then others choose the medium of three small samples  in order to get a general idea.
Otherwise, QuickSaur is coded.
Heapsaur is another comparison-based algorithm,  also known as selectionSaur using the right data structure.
So, yeah.
But first, let's talk about the heap data structure in computer science.
Heap is a tree-based data structure  where all levels are filled except the lowest  and is filled from the left to right,  often used in priority cues.
Max heap is the same concept,  but where the highest numbers start at the top  and lower numbers are pushed down.
And this data structure is used all the time  to give fast operations  as well as a great priority management.
Okay, so here's how heap sort works.
Heapsaur will take an unsorted array  and then start building a max heap  in a process called heapify.
I know, very creative.
This process will constantly validate  if the tree is following proper guidelines  for how a max heap works.
Once the tree is built,  the top element switches with the element at the end.
The heap is then rebuilt and the numbers switch again.
Rinse and repeat until sorted.
And this means that the worst and best case scenario  is a big O and log N.  Almost exactly like insertionSaur,  but doesn't do linear scan of unsorted numbers.
Instead, using the data structure, it provides.
Okay, that was a lot of explaining.
Okay, countingSaur is kind of hilarious,  so here's how it works.
CountingSaur consists of three arrays.
The unsorted array, the counting array,  also known as a collection, and the output array.
First, we define the maximum value in the array.
This defines the size of the counting array.
You iterate over the unsorted array  and for each element,  you add to the count in the counting array.
We then calculate the sum of each number  to the number to the right sequentially.
These numbers represent the amount of numbers before it.
Then we go in reverse order in the input array,  where we insert in the index that is specified  by the value of the number.
Then, subtract by one.
Repeat until everything is sorted.
So the worst-case scenario is big O and plus K,  where K is the range of the smallest number  and the largest number.
It's a funny one,  but sadly, it only works on integer values.
You can't use it to sort colors or names, whatever.
ShellSaur is an in-place comparison algorithm  that is a lot like insertionSaur,  but on steroids.
It works by using intervals.
This starts with the length of the array divided by two.
We then compare the first of each array within the given interval.
If the first number is larger than the second, it swaps.
This array then looks like this.
We then divide our interval in half again  with four elements per sublist.
We iterate over and sort each.
When interval hits one,  we use insertionSaur in order to sort the whole array.
So the best scenario is big O and log N,  while the worst-case scenario is big O and squared.
And the reason why this goes so fast  despite using insertionSaur is  because it creates a partially sorted array  before it does that final sort.
TimSaur was made in 2002  and is still being used to this day in Python.
Well, except for 3.11 plus.
TimSaur separates an array into small sub arrays called runs.
These runs are then sorted using insertionSaur.
Once all the runs have been sorted,  it then starts to use mergeSaur on the two smallest arrays.
After those have been sorted,  it takes the next run and source it into the merged array.
Rinse and repeat until everything's been sorted.
So TimSaur has an average performance of big O and log N.  And TimSaur works really fast  because it gives insertionSaur and mergeSaur a partially sorted  or a smaller array to work with.
Also, the inventor of TimSaur  named it after himself.
Tim Peters.
That's like the biggest flex of all time.
Come on.
So RaticSaur works a lot like countingSaur,  except it's a little bit weird.
RaticSaur starts looking at the last digit in the array  and then source it by that number.
It then looks at the number before the last analyzed number  and then uses that to sort the array again.
And if during an iteration a number is not present,  it just treats it like a zero.
It keeps doing this over and over and over again  until the array is fully sorted.
And the time complexity for RaticSaur is a big O,  sorry, one second, D times N plus B.  D is the amount of numbers in the largest number  and is the number of elements  and B is the base of the numbers being used.
So 10 will represent zero to nine.
And just like a lot of the algorithms  we've already talked about,  RaticSaur can be used in parallel to go even faster.
And fun fact, RaticSaur is old  and I mean really old.
Like around 1887 old.
It was also used in the old IBM punch card machines  that go all the way back to the 1920s.
Let me know in the comments if you want me to go a little bit more  in depth on these algorithms.
Let me know what concept you want me to easily explain on this channel.
If you're interested, I have a video  where I give 40 APIs you should use for your next project  as well as a video where I give $10,000  to the worst trading bot I've ever built.